K-2/53, cross road number-19 Telco Jamshedpur, IN 831004 +91-7257830471 md.altamash7257@gmail.com

MD ALTAMASH (Software Developer Engineer)

Interest:

• Al in Healthcare: I am deeply interested in using Al to revolutionize healthcare by predicting potential health issues based on a patient's history. My goal is to create advanced tools that enable personalized care, offering proactive interventions tailored to individual needs. By leveraging Al, I aim to make healthcare more effective and accessible, particularly by developing systems that can handle primary consultations. This approach allows doctors to focus their expertise on more critical cases, while Al-driven tools manage routine health concerns, ultimately improving the overall efficiency and reach of healthcare services

Personal Profile:

I'm really excited about the intersection of technology and research. With over 4 years in **Software Development, Machine Learning, and Data Analytics**, I've had the chance to dive deep into some fascinating projects involving **AI and image processing**. For my M.Tech, I worked on using **blockchain to make medical data more secure, aiming to protect it from hackers**. I'm driven to develop **innovative AI solutions to tackle cyber threats especially those that are powered by AI and improve healthcare by predicting health issues and providing personalized care so that real Doctors have time to attend more critical cases**. I'm eager to start a PhD so I can explore these interests further and contribute to innovative research that makes a difference.

Education:

• MTech, Computer Science and Engineering Institute Name: BIT MESRA

2019-2021

- **1.** I Specialize in **Machine Learning** from coursera.
- **2**. Research Focus was on using Blockchain to build a centralized system which could store medical data of a patient and keep it **safe from hackers**.
- BTech, Computer Science and Engineering Institute Name: Kolhan University

2014-2018

- 1. Qualified **Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering**: An entrance test in India for Admission in Premium institutes for Mtech.
- 2. In my Final year project we built the online portal For education with features like live online teaching which was unique at that time and was over national newspapers for this achievement.
- 3. I was awarded the **best coder** in the entire college.

Relevant Skills:

- Machine Learning and AI: Tensorflow, OpenCv, Keras, Scikit learn, Machine Learning Algorithms.
- Data Analytics: Numpy, Pandas, MatplotLib, Seaborn
- Cyber Security: Threat Detection, Security Algorithms, Vulnerability Assessment
- BlockChain Technology: Blockchain Implementation, Securedata Storage
- Programming Languages: C++, Java, Python, Sql, MongoDb
- Libraries and Frameworks: Spring Boot, spring JPA, java Servlets, jsp, junit, Spring security,

ison

- Tools: Tableau, SQL Server, ms excel, version control, Data Analysis, postman
- Other Skills: Data Analysis, Data Representation, Image Processing, Problem Solving, Software Development and automation problem solving, Agile Methodologies, rest api, soap, Microservices, multi threading, database design, System Design

Work Experience:

Software Development Engineer (ATX Learning)

08/2024 to present

- Worked on Project related to Data analysis of the employees done complete full stack solution from reading data from database to its view on the dashboard developed this using Python, Sql, PHP, Laravel, Html, css, JavaScript, BootStrap.
- Generated an Al voice assistant to handle the incoming calls book appointment automatically
 without human intervention the Ai agent would talk like a human build using Vapi Ai, Twilio,
 Make, also used open source Ai like chat Gpt.
- Currently working on Drone based system where the Drone would collect images and process
 it using ML. currently this project is in Requirement gathering and planning phase.
- Developed Drone Management System using NextJs. Used Python to analyze the Inputs and predict Results based on the MI Models. This Saves the manual work by 50%.

Assistant Professor (Research and Development) (Lovely Professional University)

10/2023 to 05/2024

- Taught Data Structures algorithms and Java to Under Grad students.
- Designed and Developed an Attendance Solution app using Java, Spring Boot and JPA, benefiting 2000 teachers.
- Developed an Examination Seating Management System in java, Impacting 28000 students with randomised seating and unique student codes.

Data Analyst (Life Gen Bio)

01/2023 to 08/2023

- Managed and Wrote Queries, handling large datasets of PostgreSQI, improving data retrieval efficiency
- * Developed dashboards in Tableau and **automated analysis Process** increasing data visualization and decision-making speed.
- * Collaborated with the team to implement actions based on analysis insights, improving team efficiency.
- * Identified KPI's and managed critical points leading to a focussed Approach and improved performance tracking.
- * Generated charts, graphs and dashboards to visually present findings, aiding in clear communication of insights
- * **Applied machine learning algorithms** to predict future trends enabling proactive Decision making.
- * Produced detailed reports and summaries for stake holders facilitating informed decision making

Programmer Analyst, (Cognizant)

- implemented deep learning models using TensorFlow and other NLP related works.
- implemented end to end from **n-gram generations** to **model building** and deploying it in UAT environment.
- implemented backend for report generation using **SQL from SQL server(ssms)**.
- implemented part of **confidence score calibration** where my responsibility was to change the **confidence score** based on **ngrams** using Python.
- Developed java applications and worked on back-end using JDBC
- Implemented **Dry Run of System** and debugging and testing the Codes using Java.
- implemented Ui-path orchestrator to keep logs in check and communicate with business monthly report of the run.
- implemented code fixes in case of any issue using Java.
- Implemented orchestrator logs to keep the project in check and communicate with business with monthly report of the run used python for my work saved 5 manual working hours per month.
- Developed auto Password reset Software using Ui path for the clients that saved more than 20 manual hours per month.

Data Science Analyst Intern (Sparks Foundation)

03/2021 - 04/2021

- Implemented **Supervised Machine Learning Algorithms** to Predict the prices of different commodities **used Python**, **Pandas**, **Keras**, **NumPy & Math Plot lib** on Jupyter Notebook to accomplish this
- Developed Charts from the Database raw Data's to create Interactive charts for Business Used Tableau, SQL, this way of creating Charts saved more than 4 hours Daily to manually collect data and create charts.

Graduate Assistantship, (Bit Mesra)

06/2019 - 06/2021

- Supporting professors with **research**, often involving **data collection**, **analysis**, **and interpretation**.
- Utilizing educational software and tools, which can translate to proficiency in data analysis tools.
- managed student data for handling large datasets in data science projects.
- Used research methodologies to gather and analyze data, similar to performing data-driven research in data science.

Data Science Analyst, 06/2018 - 06/2019 **(DPMI)**

- Creating data adapters for different data sources
- Performing exploratory and targeted data analyses, visualizing data, identifying correlations
- Training, testing, and deployment of data-driven models using python language.
- Developing data science applications that are based on statistical methods or ML/AI models
- Evaluate and report on key metrics.
- Designed and developed automated KPI dashboards to provide insights at scale
- Advocating for continuous data quality improvement via identifying data discrepancies
- Recommending improving existing data-collection methodologies

Software Intern, 05/2017 - 06/2017

(Tata Technologies Limited)

- Developed Application To manage the Orders of the Tata Motors Complete Order Management System. Using Java, Spring.
- The above-mentioned Application hand an Impact on The Complete Tata Motors Company and saved time to manage Order.

RESEARCH PAPER

• ICAIAT 2024, Research paper was published (Revolutionizing Health Engagement: The Integration of AI Health -companions with Character Creation, Real-time Chat, and Subscription Model). The conference of ICAIAT was held on 24th and 25th may 2024.

PROJECTS

Split Wise -

An application to manage expenses between friends this application allowed a group to manage expenses and split them among all the participants such that the record of group expenses is kept and everyone shares equally among the spends.

Developed using java, springboot, jpa, mysql.

Parking Lot Management System:-

Implemented a Parking lot software Design using Solid principles to have the best design and this would save the parking lot from getting over crowded i.e the person would know whether any spot is vacant or not apart from this it would also save more than 15k pm implemented using java, Spring boot, Solid Principle and MVC

Healthcare Insurance Analysis:-

Developed this Solution to predict the Insurance cost based on patient medical conditions and history This application would help the company better analyse the risk in giving an insurance to any person so that the risk is minimised this was a complete project involving data collection data cleaning, ML model building and finally predicting the outcome.

Implemented using Python for Data Science Packages: Scikit-learn, NumPy, pandas, NLTK,

Beautiful Soup, Matplotlib, Tensor Flow, Keras, CatBoost, XGBoost, GradientBoost, NLP

ACHIEVEMENTS:-

- Received Appreciation Certificate in cognizant for my valuable contribution in Project Twice.
- Received GP Birla Scholarship thrice during my masters for attaining high Grades
- Received national level Scholarship for attaining good Rank in Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering Exam this gave me the opportunity to work as a Graduate assistant and receive monthly Stipend.
- Received Scholar of the year twice from TATA MOTORS
- Received Gold Medal in International Science Olympiad with International Rank 200
- Received Gold Medal in International Mathematics Olympiad with International Rank 699
- Received Gold medal in International Cyber Olympiad with International Rank 1030
- Received **Distinction** in Mathematics from the university of new south wales
- Received many awards under different categories During the tech Fest of my university with main being best Coder Award in the entire college.
- Apart from academics Have won many Prizes in Sports categories like (400M sprint, 4x100 m relay race, basketball, volleyball, chess and carrom)